<?xml version="1.0" encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.2//EN"
		"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<article>
<articleinfo>
	<title>MySQL++ User Manual</title>
	
	<authorgroup>
		<author>
			<firstname>Kevin</firstname>
			<surname>Atkinson</surname>
		</author>

		<author>
			<firstname>Sinisa</firstname>
			<surname>Milivojevic</surname>
		</author>

		<author>
			<firstname>Monty</firstname>
			<surname>Widenius</surname>
		</author>

		<author>
			<firstname>Warren</firstname>
			<surname>Young</surname>
		</author>
	</authorgroup>

	<copyright>
		<year>1998-2001, 2005</year>
		<holder>Kevin Atkinson</holder>
		<holder>MySQL AB</holder>
		<holder>Educational Technology Resources</holder>
	</copyright>

	<pubdate role="rcs">$Date: 2005-05-26 07:28:32 -0600 (Thu, 26 May 2005) $</pubdate>
</articleinfo>


<?hard-pagebreak?>
<sect1>
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>MySQL++ is a powerful C++ wrapper for MySQL's C API.
	Its purpose is to make working with queries as easy as working
	with STL containers.</para>

	<para>The latest version of MySQL++ can be found at
	<ulink url="http://tangentsoft.net/mysql++/">the official web
	site</ulink>.</para>

	<para>Support for MySQL++ can be had on <ulink
	url="http://lists.mysql.com/plusplus">the mailing
	list</ulink>. That page hosts the mailing list archives, and
	tells you how you can subscribe.</para>


	<sect2>
		<title>A Brief History of MySQL++</title>

		<para>MySQL++ was created in 1998 by Kevin Atkinson. It
		started out MySQL-specific, but there were early efforts
		to try and make it database-independent, and call it
		SQL++. This is where the old library name "sqlplus"
		came from. This is also why the old versions prefixed
		some class names with "Mysql" but not others: the others
		were supposed to be the database-independent parts.</para>

		<para>Then in 1999, Sinisa Milivojevic unofficially took
		over maintenance of the library, releasing versions
		1.0 and 1.1. (All of Kevin's releases were pre-1.0
		point releases.) Kevin gave over maintenance to Sinisa
		officially with 1.2, and Sinisa went on to maintain the
		library through 1.7.9, released in mid-2001. Since Sinisa
		is an employee of <ulink url="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL
		AB</ulink>, it seems to be during this time that the
		dream of multiple-database compatibility died.</para>

		<para>With version 1.7.9, MySQL++ went into a period of
		stasis, lasting over three years. During this time, Sinisa
		ran the MySQL++ mailing list and supported its users, but
		made no new releases. There were many patches submitted
		during this period, some of which were ignored, others
		which were just put on the MySQL++ web site for people to
		try. A lot of these patches were mutually-incompatible,
		and not all of them gave a fully-functional copy of
		MySQL++. Most of them centered on GCC compatibility,
		because GCC 3 was created around this same time. The
		continual tightening of the rules starting with GCC 3.0
		exposed a lot of places in MySQL++ that used deprecated
		and non-conforming facilities.</para>

		<para>In early August of 2004, the current maintainer
		(Warren Young) got fed up with this situation and took
		over. He released 1.7.10 later that month.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>If You Have Questions...</title>

		<para>If you want to email someone to ask questions about
		this library, we greatly prefer that you send mail to
		the <ulink url="http://lists.mysql.com/plusplus">MySQL++
		mailing list</ulink>. The mailing list is archived,
		so if you have questions, do a search to see if the
		question has been asked before.</para>

		<para>You may find people's individual email addresses in
		various files within the MySQL++ distribution. Please do
		not send mail to them unless you are sending something
		that is inherently personal. Questions that are about
		MySQL++ usage may well be ignored if you send them to
		our personal email accounts. Those of us still active
		in MySQL++ development monitor the mailing list, so you
		aren't getting any extra "coverage" by sending messages
		to those addresses in addition to the mailing list.</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>


<?hard-pagebreak?>
<sect1>
	<title>Overview</title>

	<para>MySQL++ has developed into a very complex and powerful
	library, with many different ways to accomplish the same
	task. Unfortunately, this means that figuring out how to perform
	a simple task can be frustrating for new users. In this section
	we will provide an overview of the most important user-facing
	components of the library.</para>

	<para>The overall process for using MySQL++ is similar to that of
	most other database access APIs:</para>
	
	<orderedlist>
		<listitem><para>Open the connection</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Form and execute the query</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Iterate through the result set</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>Go to 2 :)</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	<para>There is, however, a lot of extra functionality along each
	step of the way.</para>


	<sect2>
		<title>The Connection Object</title>

		<para>A <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Connection.html">Connection</ulink>
		object manages the connection to the MySQL server. You
		need at least one of these objects to do anything. A
		Connection object can either create Query objects for
		you, or you can execute queries directly through the
		Connection object. The separate Query object is the
		recommended way as it gives you far more power.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>The Query Object</title>

		<para>A <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Query.html">Query</ulink>
		object is the recommended way of building
		and executing queries. It is subclassed from
		<computeroutput>std::stringstream</computeroutput>
		which means you can write to it like any other
		C++ stream to form a query. The library includes
		<ulink url="../../refman/html/manip_8h.html">stream
		manipulators</ulink> that make it easy to generate
		syntactically-correct SQL.</para>

		<para>You can also set up <xref linkend="tquery"/> with
		this class. Template queries work something like the
		C <computeroutput>printf()</computeroutput> function:
		you set up a fixed query string with tags inside that
		indicate where to insert the variable parts. If you
		have multiple queries that are structurally similar,
		you simply set up one template query, and use that in
		the various locations of your program.</para>

		<para>A third method for building queries is to
		use <xref linkend="ssqls"/> (SSQLS). This feature
		presents your results as a C++ data structure, instead of
		making you access the data through MySQL++ intermediary
		classes. It also reduces the amount of embedded SQL code
		your program needs.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Result Sets</title>

		<para>The field data in a result set are stored in a
		special <computeroutput>std::string</computeroutput>-like
		class called <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1ColData__Tmpl.html">ColData</ulink>.
		This class has conversion operators
		that let you automatically convert these
		objects to any of the basic C data types.
		Additionally, MySQL++ defines classes like <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/structmysqlpp_1_1DateTime.html">DateTime</ulink>,
		which you can initialize from a MySQL
		<computeroutput>DATETIME</computeroutput> string. These
		automatic conversions are protected against bad
		conversions, and can either set a warning flag or throw an
		exception, depending on how you set the library up.</para>

		<para>As for the result sets as a whole, MySQL++ has a
		number of different ways of representing them:</para>

		<sect3>
			<title>Queries That Do Not Return Data</title>

			<para>Not all SQL queries return data. An
			example is <computeroutput>CREATE
			TABLE</computeroutput>. For these
			types of queries, there is a <ulink
			url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1ResNSel.html">special
			result type</ulink> that simply reports the
			state resulting from the query: whether the
			query was successful, how many rows it impacted
			(if any), etc.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Queries That Return Data: Dynamic Method</title>

			<para>The easiest way to
			retrieve data from MySQL uses a <ulink
			url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Result.html">Result</ulink>
			object, which includes one or more <ulink
			url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Row.html">Row</ulink>
			objects. Because these classes are
			<computeroutput>std::vector</computeroutput>-like
			containers, you can treat the result set as a
			two-dimensional array. For example, you can get
			the 5th item on the 2nd row by simply saying
			<computeroutput>result[1][4]</computeroutput>. You
			can also access row elements
			by field name, like this:
			<computeroutput>result[2].lookup_by_name("price")</computeroutput>.</para>

			<para>An alternate way of accessing
			your query results is through a <ulink
			url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1ResUse.html">ResUse</ulink>
			object. This class acts more like an STL input
			iterator than a container: you walk through
			your result set one item at a time, always going
			forward. You can't seek around in the result set,
			and you can't know how many results are in the
			set until you find the end. This method is more
			efficient when there can be arbitrarily many
			results, which could pose a memory allocation
			problem with the previous technique.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Queries That Return Data: Static Method</title>

			<para>The <xref linkend="ssqls"/> (SSQLS) feature
			method above defines C++ structures that match the
			table structures in your database schema.</para>

			<para>We call it the "static" method because the
			table structure is fixed at compile time. Indeed,
			some schema changes require that you update your
			SSQLS definitions and recompile, or else the
			program could crash or throw "bad conversion"
			exceptions when MySQL++ tries to stuff the new
			data into an outdated data structure.  (Not all
			changes require a recompile. Adding a column to
			a table is safe, for instance, as the program
			will ignore the new column until you update the
			SSQLS definition.)</para>

			<para>The advantage of this method is that
			your program will require very little embedded
			SQL code. You can simply execute a query, and
			receive your results as C++ data structures,
			which can be accessed just as you would any
			other structure. The results can be accessed
			through the Row object, or you can ask the
			library to dump the results into a sequential
			or set-associative STL container for you. Consider
			this:</para>

			<programlisting>
    vector&lt;mystruct&gt; v;
    Query q = connection.query();
    q &lt;&lt; "SELECT * FROM mytable";
    q.storein(v);
    for (vector&lt;mystruct&gt;::iterator it = v.begin(); it != v.end(); ++v) {
        cout &lt;&lt; "Price: " &lt;&lt; it-&gt;price &lt;&lt; endl;
    }</programlisting>

			<para>Isn't that slick?</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Exceptions</title>

		<para>By default, the library throws <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/exceptions_8h.html">exceptions</ulink>
		derived from
		<computeroutput>std::exception</computeroutput>
		whenever it encounters an error. You can ask the library
		to set an error flag instead, if you like, but the
		exceptions carry more information. Not only do they
		include a string member telling you why the exception
		was thrown, there are several exception types, so you
		can distinguish between different error types within a
		single <computeroutput>try</computeroutput> block.</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>


<?hard-pagebreak?>
<sect1>
	<title>Tutorial</title>

	<para>This tutorial is meant to give you a jump start in using
	MySQL++. While it is a very complicated and powerful library,
	it's possible to make quite functional programs without tapping
	but a fraction of its power. This section will introduce you to
	the most useful fraction.</para>

	<para>This tutorial assumes you know C++ fairly well,
	in particuler the Standard Template Library (STL) and
	exceptions.</para>


	<sect2>
		<title>Running the Examples</title>

		<para>All of the examples are complete running
		programs. They may or may not be built for you already,
		depending on how you installed the library.</para>

		<para>If you installed MySQL++ from the source
		tarball on a Unixy system, the examples should
		have been built along with the library. If not,
		simply go into the examples directory and type
		<computeroutput>make</computeroutput>.</para>

		<para>If you installed the library via
		RPM, the examples are in the mysql++-devel
		RPM. After installing that, the examples are in
		<computeroutput>/usr/src/mysql++/examples</computeroutput>.
		To build them, go into that directory
		and type <computeroutput>make -f
		Makefile.simple</computeroutput>. See the file
		<computeroutput>/usr/share/doc/mysql++-devel*/README.examples</computeroutput>
		for more details.</para>

		<para>If you are on a Windows system, the build process
		for the library should have built the examples as
		well. Where the programs are depends on which compiler
		you're using. There should be a README.* file in the
		distribution specific to your compiler with further
		instructions.</para>

		<para>Once you have the examples building, you need
		to initialize the sample database by running the
		<computeroutput>resetdb</computeroutput> example. The
		usage of resetdb is as follows:</para>

		<screen>	resetdb [host [user [password [port]]]]</screen>

		<para>If you leave off host, localhost is assumed. If
		you leave off user, your current username is assumed. If
		you leave of the password, it is assumed that you don't
		need one. And if you leave off the port, it will use
		the standard MySQL port number.</para>

		<para>The user you give resetdb needs to be an account
		with permission to create databases. Once the database is
		created you can use any account that has full permission
		to the sample database mysql_cpp_data.</para>

		<para>You may also have to re-run resetdb after
		running some of the other examples, as they change the
		database.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>The Basics</title>

		<sect3>
			<title>A simple example</title>

			<para>The following example demonstrates
			how to open a connection, execute a simple
			query, and display the results. This is
			examples/simple1.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;

#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;iomanip&gt;

using namespace std;

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    // Wrap all MySQL++ interactions in one big try block, so any
    // errors are handled gracefully.
    try {
        // Connect to the sample database
        mysqlpp::Connection con(mysqlpp::use_exceptions);
        if (!connect_to_db(argc, argv, con)) {
            return 1;
        }

        // Create a query object that is bound to con.
        mysqlpp::Query query = con.query();

        // Print out the stock table
        print_stock_table(query);
    }
    catch (mysqlpp::BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // handle any connection or query errors that may come up
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (mysqlpp::BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl
            &lt;&lt; "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved
            &lt;&lt; " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception &amp; er) {
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    return 0;
}</programlisting></blockquote>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>The example programs' utility module</title>

			<para>If anything, the code above is "too"
			simple, because all it really does is drive
			some functions in examples/util.cpp. Most of
			the examples link to this module, because it
			contains code that would otherwise have to be
			repeated in these examples.</para>

			<para>Here's a simplified version of the utility
			module:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;iomanip&gt;
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;

using namespace std;

const char* kpcSampleDatabase = "mysql_cpp_data";


//// print_stock_header ////////////////////////////////////////////////
// Display a header suitable for use with print_stock_rows().

void
print_stock_header(int rows)
{
    cout &lt;&lt; "Records found: " &lt;&lt; rows &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; endl;
    cout.setf(ios::left);
    cout &lt;&lt; setw(21) &lt;&lt; "Item" &lt;&lt;
            setw(10) &lt;&lt; "Num" &lt;&lt;
            setw(10) &lt;&lt; "Weight" &lt;&lt;
            setw(10) &lt;&lt; "Price" &lt;&lt;
            "Date" &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; endl;
}


//// print_stock_row ///////////////////////////////////////////////////
// Print out a row of data from the stock table, in a format
// compatbile with the header printed out in the previous function.

void
print_stock_row(const char* item, mysqlpp::longlong num, double weight,
        double price, mysqlpp::Date date)
{
    // Output first column, the item string.
    cout &lt;&lt; setw(20) &lt;&lt; item &lt;&lt; ' ' &lt;&lt;
            setw(9) &lt;&lt; num &lt;&lt; ' ' &lt;&lt;
            setw(9) &lt;&lt; weight &lt;&lt; ' ' &lt;&lt;
            setw(9) &lt;&lt; price &lt;&lt; ' ' &lt;&lt;
            date &lt;&lt; endl;
}


//// print_stock_rows //////////////////////////////////////////////////
// Print out a number of rows from the example 'stock' table.

void
print_stock_rows(mysqlpp::Result&amp; res)
{
    print_stock_header(res.size());

    // Use the Result class's read-only random access iterator to walk
    // through the query results.
    mysqlpp::Result::iterator i;
    for (i = res.begin(); i != res.end(); ++i) {
        // Convert the Result iterator into a Row object, for easier
        // access.
        mysqlpp::Row row(*i);

        // Notice that you can use either the column index or name to
        // retrieve the data.  Also notice that we do no explicit
        // conversions to match print_stock_row()'s parameter types:
        // Row elements are ColData strings, so they auto-convert to
        // any standard C++ type.
        print_stock_row(row[0], row[1], row.lookup_by_name("weight"),
                row[3], row[4]);
    }
}


//// print_stock_table /////////////////////////////////////////////////
// Print the entire contents of the example 'stock' table.

void
print_stock_table(mysqlpp::Query&amp; query)
{
    // You must reset the query object when re-using it.
    query.reset();

    // You can write to the query object like you would any ostream.
    query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock";

    // Show the query string.  If you do this, you have to do it before
    // you execute() or store() or use() it.
    cout &lt;&lt; "Query: " &lt;&lt; query.preview() &lt;&lt; endl;

    // Execute the query and display the result set.
    mysqlpp::Result res = query.store();
    print_stock_rows(res);
}


//// connect_to_db /////////////////////////////////////////////////////
// Establishes a connection to a MySQL database server, optionally
// attaching to database kdb.  This is basically a command-line parser
// for the examples, since the example programs' arguments give us the
// information we need to establish the server connection.

bool
connect_to_db(int argc, char *argv[], mysqlpp::Connection&amp; con,
        const char *kdb)
{
    if (argc &lt; 1) {
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Bad argument count: " &lt;&lt; argc &lt;&lt; '!' &lt;&lt; endl;
        return false;
    }

    if ((argc &gt; 1) &amp;&amp; (argv[1][0] == '-')) {
        cout &lt;&lt; "usage: " &lt;&lt; argv[0] &lt;&lt;
                " [host] [user] [password] [port]" &lt;&lt; endl;
        cout &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; "\tConnects to database ";
        if (kdb) {
            cout &lt;&lt; '"' &lt;&lt; kdb &lt;&lt; '"';
        }
        else {
            cout &lt;&lt; "server";
        }
        cout &lt;&lt; " on localhost using your user" &lt;&lt; endl;
        cout &lt;&lt; "\tname and no password by default." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; endl;
        return false;
    }

    if (!kdb) {
        kdb = kpcSampleDatabase;
    }

    bool success = false;
    if (argc == 1) {
        success = con.connect(kdb);
    }
    else if (argc == 2) {
        success = con.connect(kdb, argv[1]);
    }
    else if (argc == 3) {
        success = con.connect(kdb, argv[1], argv[2]);
    }
    else if (argc == 4) {
        success = con.connect(kdb, argv[1], argv[2], argv[3]);
    }
    else if (argc &gt;= 5) {
        success = con.real_connect(kdb, argv[1], argv[2], argv[3],
                atoi(argv[4]));
    }

    if (!success) {
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Database connection failed." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; endl;
    }

    return success;
}</programlisting></blockquote>

			<para>The only simplication done to the code is to remove the
			Unicode conversion stuff. That is covered in a later chapter,
			<xref linkend="unicode"/>.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Notes on exceptions</title>

			<para>Aside from driving the
			<computeroutput>connect_to_db()</computeroutput>
			and
			<computeroutput>print_stock_table()</computeroutput>
			functions in the utility module, the
			simple1 example mainly consists of exception
			handlers. This block of code will become familiar
			to you in the following examples, because it's
			identical for all of them.</para>

			<para>A few notes about exceptions:</para>

			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Exceptions are the
				default way for MySQL++ to signal
				errors, but some MySQL++ classes (<ulink
				url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Connection.html">Connection</ulink>,
				<ulink
				url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Query.html">Query</ulink>,
				<ulink
				url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Result.html">Result</ulink>,
				<ulink
				url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1ResUse.html">ResUse</ulink>,
				and <ulink
				url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Row.html">Row</ulink>)
				allow you to disable these exceptions. The
				methods vary, but some classes'
				constructors accept a flag to disable
				exceptions, some allow you to disable
				exceptions on a per-method-call basis,
				and some let you turn them on and
				off for the object with a method
				call.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>The state of the object's
				exception enabling flag is passed
				down to child objects. For example,
				if you create a Connection object with
				exceptions disabled and then call its
				<computeroutput>query()</computeroutput>
				method to get a Query object, that
				object will also have exceptions
				disabled.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>The exception enabling
				flag is copied from object to object,
				so if you create a child object and
				then change the flag in the parent,
				the child object's exception enabling
				state is not changed.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>ColData
				will always throw <ulink
				url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1BadConversion.html">an
				exception</ulink> when it is unable
				to do a requested conversion. A bad
				conversion is defined as one where: a)
				not all the characters from the string
				have yet been processed, and b) the
				remaining characters are something other
				than whitespace, zeros (0), or periods
				(.). This means that an exception is
				thrown when ``1.25'' is converted into an
				int, but not when ``1.00'' is converted
				into an int. In the latter case, MySQL++
				knows that it can safely throw away the
				fractional part.</para></listitem>

				<listitem><para>An out-of-bounds
				subscript when accessing a MySQL++
				container may throw an exception. Whether
				it does or not depends on whether
				the underlying STL container throws
				exceptions in this situation, so it's
				compiler-dependent.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>

			<para>To see how the exceptions work, try
			creating an error. Some good things to try would
			be misspelling a table name or trying to cast
			a floating-point column value to an int.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Getting info about the fields</title>

			<para>The following example demonstrates how to
			get some basic information about the fields,
			including the name of the field and the SQL
			type. This is examples/fieldinf1.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;

#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;iomanip&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    try {
        Connection con(use_exceptions);
        if (!connect_to_db(argc, argv, con)) {
            return 1;
        }

        Query query = con.query();
        query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock";
        cout &lt;&lt; "Query: " &lt;&lt; query.preview() &lt;&lt; endl;

        Result res = query.store();
        cout &lt;&lt; "Records Found: " &lt;&lt; res.size() &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; endl;

        cout &lt;&lt; "Query Info:\n";
        cout.setf(ios::left);

        for (unsigned int i = 0; i &lt; res.names().size(); i++) {
            cout &lt;&lt; setw(2) &lt;&lt; i
                    // this is the name of the field
                    &lt;&lt; setw(15) &lt;&lt; res.names(i).c_str()
                    // this is the SQL identifier name
                    // Result::types(unsigned int) returns a mysql_type_info which in many
                    // ways is like type_info except that it has additional sql type
                    // information in it. (with one of the methods being sql_name())
                    &lt;&lt; setw(15) &lt;&lt; res.types(i).sql_name()
                    // this is the C++ identifier name which most closely resembles
                    // the sql name (its is implementation defined and often not very readable)
                    &lt;&lt; setw(20) &lt;&lt; res.types(i).name()
                    &lt;&lt; endl;
        }

        cout &lt;&lt; endl;

        if (res.types(0) == typeid(string)) {
            // this is demonstrating how a mysql_type_info can be 
            // compared with a C++ type_info.
            cout &lt;&lt; "Field 'item' is of an SQL type which most "
                    "closely resembles\nthe C++ string type\n";
        }

        if (res.types(1) == typeid(longlong)) {
            cout &lt;&lt; "Field 'num' is of an SQL type which most "
                    "closely resembles\nC++ long long int type\n";
        }
        else if (res.types(1).base_type() == typeid(longlong)) {
            // you have to be careful as if it can be null the actual
            // type is Null&lt;TYPE&gt; not TYPE.  So you should always use
            // the base_type method to get at the underlying type.
            // If the type is not null than this base type would be
            // the same as its type.
            cout &lt;&lt; "Field 'num' base type is of an SQL type which "
                    "most closely\nresembles the C++ long long int type\n";
        }
    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt;
                "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved &lt;&lt;
                " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    return 0;
}</programlisting></blockquote>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Quoting and Escaping</title>

		<para>SQL syntax often requires certain data to be
		quoted. Consider this query:</para>

		<programlisting>
        SELECT * FROM stock WHERE item = 'Hotdog Buns' </programlisting>

		<para>Because the string "Hotdog Buns" contains a space,
		it must be quoted. With MySQL++, you don't have to add
		these quote marks manually:</para>

		<programlisting>
        string s = "Hotdog Buns";
        Query q = conn.query();
        q &lt;&lt; "SELECT * FROM stock WHERE item = " &lt;&lt; quote_only &lt;&lt; s; </programlisting>

		<para>That code produces the same query string
		as in the previous example. We used the MySQL++
		<computeroutput>quote_only</computeroutput>
		manipulator, which causes single quotes to be
		added around the next item inserted into the
		stream. This works for various string types, for any
		type of data that can be converted to MySQL++'s <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1ColData__Tmpl.html">ColData</ulink>
		type, and for <xref linkend="ssqls"/>. (The next section
		introduces the SSQLS feature.)</para>

		<para>Quoting is pretty simple, but SQL syntax also often
		requires that certain characters be "escaped". Imagine
		if the string in the previous example was "Frank's Brand Hotdog
		Buns" instead. The resulting query would be:</para>

		<programlisting>
        SELECT * FROM stock WHERE item = 'Frank's Brand Hotdog Buns' </programlisting>

		<para>That's not valid SQL syntax. The correct syntax is:</para>

		<programlisting>
        SELECT * FROM stock WHERE item = 'Frank''s Brand Hotdog Buns' </programlisting>

		<para>As you might expect, MySQL++ provides that feature,
		too, through its 'escape' manipulator. But here, we want
		both quoting and escaping. That brings us to the most
		widely useful manipulator:</para>

		<programlisting>
        string s = "Hotdogs' Buns";
        Query q = conn.query();
        q &lt;&lt; "SELECT * FROM stock WHERE item = " &lt;&lt; quote &lt;&lt; s; </programlisting>

		<para>The regular quote manipulator both quotes strings,
		and escapes any characters that are special in SQL.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Specialized SQL Structures</title>

		<sect3>
			<title>Retrieving data</title>

			<para>The next example introduces one of
			the most powerful features of MySQL++:
			<xref linkend="ssqls"/> (SSQLS). This is
			examples/custom1.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;
#include &lt;custom.h&gt;

#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;iomanip&gt;
#include &lt;vector&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

// The following is calling a very complex macro which will create
// "struct stock", which has the member variables:
//
//   string item
//   ...
//   Date sdate
//
// plus methods to help populate the class from a MySQL row
// among other things that I'll get to in a later example.
sql_create_5(stock,
             1, 5,              // explained in the user manual
             string, item,
             longlong, num,
             double, weight,
             double, price,
             Date, sdate)

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    try {                       
        // Establish the connection to the database server.
        Connection con(use_exceptions);
        if (!connect_to_db(argc, argv, con)) {
            return 1;
        }

        // Retrieve the entire contents of the stock table, and store
        // the data in a vector of 'stock' SSQLS structures.
        Query query = con.query();
        query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock";
        vector&lt;stock&gt; res;
        query.storein(res);

        // Display the result set
        print_stock_header(res.size());
        vector&lt;stock&gt;::iterator it;
        for (it = res.begin(); it != res.end(); ++it) {
            print_stock_row(it-&gt;item.c_str(), it-&gt;num, it-&gt;weight,
                    it-&gt;price, it-&gt;sdate);
        }
    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt;
                "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved &lt;&lt;
                " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    return 0;
}</programlisting></blockquote>
			
			<para>As you can see, SSQLS is very powerful.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Adding data</title>

			<para>SSQLS can also be used to add data to a table. This
			is examples/custom2.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;
#include &lt;custom.h&gt;

#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;string&gt;
#include &lt;vector&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

sql_create_5(stock,
            1, 5,
            string, item,
            longlong, num,
            double, weight,
            double, price,
            Date, sdate)

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    try {
        // Establish the connection to the database server.
        Connection con(use_exceptions);
        if (!connect_to_db(argc, argv, con)) {
            return 1;
        }

        // Create and populate a stock object.  We could also have used
        // the set() member, which takes the same parameters as this
        // constructor.
        stock row("Hot Dogs", 100, 1.5, 1.75, "1998-09-25");

        // Form the query to insert the row into the stock table.
        Query query = con.query();
        query.insert(row);

        // Show the query about to be executed.
        cout &lt;&lt; "Query: " &lt;&lt; query.preview() &lt;&lt; endl;

        // Execute the query.  We use execute() because INSERT doesn't
        // return a result set.
        query.execute();

        // Print the new table.
        print_stock_table(query);
    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (BadConversion&amp; er) { 
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt;
                "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved &lt;&lt;
                " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    return 0;
}</programlisting></blockquote>

			<para>That's all there is to it!</para>
			
			<para>There is one subtlety: MySQL++ automatically
			quotes and escapes the data when building SQL
			queries using SSQLS structures. It's efficient,
			too: MySQL++ is smart enough to apply quoting
			and escaping only for those data types that
			actually require it.</para>

			<para>Because this example modifies the sample
			database, you may want to run resetdb after
			running this program.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Modifying data</title>

			<para>It almost as easy to modify data with
			SSQLS. This is examples/custom3.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;
#include &lt;custom.h&gt;

#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;string&gt;
#include &lt;vector&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

sql_create_5(stock,
            1, 5,
            string, item,
            longlong, num,
            double, weight,
            double, price,
            Date, sdate)

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    try {
        // Establish the connection to the database server.
        Connection con(use_exceptions);
        if (!connect_to_db(argc, argv, con)) {
            return 1;
        }

        // Build a query to retrieve the stock item that has Unicode
        // characters encoded in UTF-8 form.
        Query query = con.query();
        query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock where item = \"Nürnberger Brats\"";

        // Retrieve the row, throwing an exception if it fails.
        Result res = query.store();
        if (res.empty()) {
            throw BadQuery("UTF-8 bratwurst item not found in "
                    "table, run resetdb");
        }

        // Because there should only be one row in the result set,
        // there's no point in storing the result in an STL container.
        // We can store the first row directly into a stock structure
        // because one of an SSQLS's constructors takes a Row object.
        stock row = res[0];

        // Create a copy so that the replace query knows what the
        // original values are.
        stock orig_row = row;

        // Change the stock object's item to use only 7-bit ASCII, and
        // to deliberately be wider than normal column widths printed
        // by print_stock_table().
        row.item = "Nuerenberger Bratwurst";

        // Form the query to replace the row in the stock table.
        query.update(orig_row, row);

        // Show the query about to be executed.
        cout &lt;&lt; "Query: " &lt;&lt; query.preview() &lt;&lt; endl;

        // Run the query with execute(), since UPDATE doesn't return a
        // result set.
        query.execute();

        // Print the new table contents.
        print_stock_table(query);
    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt;
                "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved &lt;&lt;
                " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    return 0;
}</programlisting></blockquote>

			<para>When you run the example you will notice
			that in the WHERE clause only the 'item' field
			is checked for. This is because SSQLS also also
			less-than-comparable.</para>

			<para>Don't forget to run resetdb after running
			the example.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Less-than-comparable</title>

			<para>SSQLS structures can be sorted and stored in
			STL associative containers as demonstrated in the
			next example. This is custom4.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;
#include &lt;custom.h&gt;

#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;iomanip&gt;
#include &lt;string&gt;
#include &lt;vector&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

sql_create_5(stock,
    1,  // This number is used to make a SSQLS less-than-comparable.
        // When comparing two SSQLS structures, the first N elements are
        // compared.  In this instance, we are saying that we only want
        // the first element ('item') to be used when comparing two
        // stock structures.

    5,  // Each SSQLS structure includes a number of constructors.  Some
        // of these are fixed in nature, but one of these will have this
        // number of arguments, one for each of the first N elements in
        // the structure; it is an initialization ctor.  Since N is the
        // same as the number of structure elements in this instance,
        // that ctor will be able to fully initialize the structure. This
        // behavior is not always wanted, however, so the macro allows
        // you make the constructor take fewer parameters, leaving the
        // remaining elements uninitialized.  An example of when this is
        // necessary is when you have a structure containing only two
        // integer elements: one of the other ctors defined for SSQLS
        // structures takes two ints, so the compiler barfs if you pass
        // 2 for this argument.  You would need to pass 0 here to get
        // that SSQLS structure to compile.
    string, item,
    longlong, num,
    double, weight,
    double, price,
    Date, sdate)

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    try {
        // Establish the connection to the database server.
        Connection con(use_exceptions);
        if (!connect_to_db(argc, argv, con)) {
            return 1;
        }

        // Retrieve all rows from the stock table and put them in an
        // STL set.  Notice that this works just as well as storing them
        // in a vector, which we did in custom1.cpp.  It works because
        // SSQLS objects are less-than comparable.
        Query query = con.query();
        query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock";
        set&lt;stock&gt; res;
        query.storein(res);

        // Display the result set.  Since it is an STL set and we set up
        // the SSQLS to compare based on the item column, the rows will
        // be sorted by item.
        print_stock_header(res.size());
        set&lt;stock&gt;::iterator it;
        cout.precision(3);
        for (it = res.begin(); it != res.end(); ++it) {
            print_stock_row(it-&gt;item.c_str(), it-&gt;num, it-&gt;weight,
                    it-&gt;price, it-&gt;sdate);
        }

        // Use set's find method to look up a stock item by item name.
        // This also uses the SSQLS comparison setup.
        it = res.find(stock("Hotdog Buns"));
        if (it != res.end()) {
            cout &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; "Currently " &lt;&lt; it-&gt;num &lt;&lt;
                    " hotdog buns in stock." &lt;&lt; endl;
        }
        else {
            cout &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; "Sorry, no hotdog buns in stock." &lt;&lt; endl;
        }
    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt;
                "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved &lt;&lt;
                " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    return 0;
}</programlisting></blockquote>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Handling SQL Nulls</title>

		<para>There is no equivalent of SQL's null in the standard
		C++ type system.</para>

		<para>The primary distinction is one of type: in SQL,
		null is a column attribute, which affects whether
		that column can hold a SQL null. This effectively
		doubles the number of types in SQL. MySQL++ handles
		this the same way SQL does: it provides the <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1null.html">Null</ulink>
		template to allow the creation of distinct "nullable"
		versions of existing C++ types. For each column type
		MySQL understands, the library instantiates this
		template for the closest C++ type. (See the top of
		<computeroutput>lib/type_info.cpp</computeroutput>
		for the list.)</para>

		<para>Template instantiations are first-class types in
		the C++ language, on par with any other type. You can
		use nullable MySQL++ types anywhere you'd use the plain
		version of that type, you can assign plain values to a
		nullable object and vice versa, etc.</para>

		<para>There's a secondary distinction between SQL null and
		anything available in the standard C++ type system: SQL
		null is a distinct value, equal to nothing else. C++'s
		<computeroutput>NULL</computeroutput> is ambiguous,
		being equal to 0 in integer context, so MySQL++ has
		a global <computeroutput>null</computeroutput> object
		which which you can assign to any nullable object to
		get a SQL null.</para>

		<para>By default, if you try to convert a SQL
		null to a plain C++ data type, MySQL++ will throw a <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1BadNullConversion.html">BadNullConversion</ulink>
		exception to enforce this distinction. If you insert
		a SQL null into a C++ stream, you get "(NULL)". The <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/structmysqlpp_1_1NullisNull.html">NullisNull</ulink>
		"behavior" type encapsulates these two
		rules; it is the default for one of template
		<computeroutput>Null</computeroutput>'s
		parameters. To relax this distinction, you can
		instantiate the <computeroutput>Null</computeroutput>
		template with a different behavior type: <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/structmysqlpp_1_1NullisZero.html">NullisZero</ulink>
		or <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/structmysqlpp_1_1NullisBlank.html">NullisBlank</ulink>.
		As you might guess from their names, SQL nulls using
		these behaviors get converted to 0 or a blank C string,
		respectively.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Which Query Type to Use?</title>

		<para>There are three major ways to execute a query in MySQL++:
		<computeroutput>Query::execute()</computeroutput>,
		<computeroutput>Query::store()</computeroutput>, and
		<computeroutput>Query::use()</computeroutput>. Which should you
		use, and why?</para>

		<para><computeroutput>execute()</computeroutput>
		is for queries that do not return data <emphasis>per
		se</emphasis>. For instance, <computeroutput>CREATE
		INDEX</computeroutput>. You do get back some
		information from the MySQL server, which
		<computeroutput>execute()</computeroutput>
		returns to its caller in a <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1ResNSel.html">ResNSel</ulink>
		object. In addition to the obvious &mdash; a flag stating
		whether the query succeeded or not &mdash; this object also
		contains things like the number of rows that the query
		affected. If you only need the success status, there's
		<computeroutput>Query::exec()</computeroutput>, which
		just returns bool.</para>

		<para>If your query does pull data from
		the database, the simplest option is
		<computeroutput>store()</computeroutput>.
		This returns a <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1Result.html">Result</ulink>
		object, which contains an in-memory copy of
		the result set. The nice thing about this is
		that <computeroutput>Result</computeroutput>
		is a sequential container, like
		<computeroutput>std::vector</computeroutput>, so you
		can iterate through it forwards and backwards, access
		elements with subscript notation, etc. There are also
		the <computeroutput>storein()</computeroutput> methods,
		which actually put the result set into an STL container
		of your choice. The downside of these methods is that
		a sufficiently large result set will give your program
		memory problems.</para>

		<para>For these large result sets, you should
		use the <computeroutput>use()</computeroutput>
		method instead. This returns a <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1ResUse.html">ResUse</ulink>
		object, which is similar to Result, but without all of
		the random-access features. This is because a "use"
		query tells the database server to send the results
		back one row at a time, to be processed linearly. It's
		analogous to a C++ stream's input iterator, as opposed
		to a random-access iterator that a container like
		vector offers. By accepting this limitation, you can process
		arbitrarily large result sets.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Let's Do Something Useful</title>

		<para>These next few examples demonstrate just how powerful
		C++ can be, allowing you to do a lot of work in few lines of
		code without losing efficiency.</para>

		<para>Since the code is meant to be re-used as-is,
		constants that can differ from one case to another have
		been grouped in order to simplify editing. Also, all of
		these examples have full error checking code, showing off
		the power of MySQL++'s exception handling features.</para>

		<sect3>
			<title>Loading binary file in a BLOB column</title>

			<para>Since MySQL 3.23, BLOB columns have
			been available, but their use is sometimes not
			straightforward. Besides showing how easy it
			can be with MySQL++, this example demonstrates
			several features of MySQL++. The program requires
			one command line parameter, which is a full path
			to the binary file. This is examples/load_file.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;

#include &lt;sys/stat.h&gt;

#include &lt;fstream&gt;

#include &lt;errno.h&gt;
#include &lt;stdlib.h&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

const char MY_DATABASE[] = "telcent";
const char MY_TABLE[] = "fax";
const char MY_HOST[] = "localhost";
const char MY_USER[] = "root";
const char MY_PASSWORD[] = "";
const char MY_FIELD[] = "fax";  // BLOB field

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    if (argc &lt; 2) {
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Usage : load_file full_file_path" &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    Connection con(use_exceptions);
    try {
        con.real_connect(MY_DATABASE, MY_HOST, MY_USER, MY_PASSWORD, 3306,
                         0, 60, NULL);
        Query query = con.query();
        ostringstream strbuf;
        ifstream In(argv[1], ios::in | ios::binary);
        struct stat for_len;
        if ((In.rdbuf())-&gt;is_open()) {
            if (stat(argv[1], &amp;for_len) == -1)
                return -1;
            unsigned int blen = for_len.st_size;
            if (!blen)
                return -1;
            char *read_buffer = new char[blen];
            In.read(read_buffer, blen);
            string fill(read_buffer, blen);
            strbuf &lt;&lt; "INSERT INTO " &lt;&lt; MY_TABLE &lt;&lt; " (" &lt;&lt; MY_FIELD &lt;&lt;
                ") VALUES(\"" &lt;&lt; mysqlpp::escape &lt;&lt; fill &lt;&lt; "\")" &lt;&lt; ends;
            query.exec(strbuf.str());
            delete[]read_buffer;
        }
        else
            cerr &lt;&lt; "Your binary file " &lt;&lt; argv[1] &lt;&lt;
                "could not be open, errno = " &lt;&lt; errno;
        return 0;

    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; " " &lt;&lt; con.errnum() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt;
                "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved &lt;&lt;
                " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
} </programlisting></blockquote>

			<para>Notice that we used the
			<computeroutput>escape</computeroutput>
			manipulator when building the INSERT query
			above. This is because we're not using one of
			the MySQL++ types that does automatic escaping
			and quoting.</para>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>Displaying images in HTML from BLOB column</title>

			<para>This example is also a very short
			one, considering the function that it
			performs. Although all modern versions of
			MySQL have a command that dumps data from a BLOB
			column to a binary file, this example shows
			how to do it in your code instead, without
			requiring an temporary file on disk. This is
			examples/cgi_image.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

#define MY_DATABASE "telcent"
#define MY_TABLE    "fax"
#define MY_HOST     "localhost"
#define MY_USER     "root"
#define MY_PASSWORD ""
#define MY_FIELD    "fax"       // BLOB field
#define MY_KEY      "datet"     // PRIMARY KEY

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    if (argc &lt; 2) {
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Usage : cgi_image primary_key_value" &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    cout &lt;&lt; "Content-type: image/jpeg" &lt;&lt; endl;
    Connection con(use_exceptions);
    try {
        con.real_connect(MY_DATABASE, MY_HOST, MY_USER, MY_PASSWORD, 3306,
                         0, 60, NULL);
        Query query = con.query();
        query &lt;&lt; "SELECT " &lt;&lt; MY_FIELD &lt;&lt; " FROM " &lt;&lt; MY_TABLE &lt;&lt; " WHERE "
            &lt;&lt; MY_KEY &lt;&lt; " = " &lt;&lt; argv[1];
        ResUse res = query.use();
        Row row = res.fetch_row();
        long unsigned int *jj = res.fetch_lengths();
        cout &lt;&lt; "Content-length: " &lt;&lt; *jj &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt; endl;
        fwrite(row.raw_data(0), 1, *jj, stdout);
        return 0;
    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; " " &lt;&lt; con.errnum() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
} </programlisting></blockquote>
		</sect3>

		<sect3>
			<title>DELETE or UPDATE from SELECT</title>

			<para>MySQL's SELECT statement has more power to
			winnow out just the items of interest from the
			database than do DELETE or UPDATE queries. Therefore,
			many people have wanted the ability to execute a
			SELECT statement that in fact deletes or updates
			the rows matched, rather than returning them. This
			example implements that feature in just a few
			lines of code. It is examples/updel.cpp:</para>

			<blockquote><programlisting>
#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;

#include &lt;string&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

#define MY_DATABASE "telcent"
#define MY_TABLE    "nazivi"
#define MY_HOST     "localhost"
#define MY_USER     "root"
#define MY_PASSWORD ""
#define MY_FIELD    "naziv"
#define MY_QUERY    "SELECT URL from my_table as t1, my_table as t2 where t1.field = t2.field"

int
main()
{
    Connection con(use_exceptions);
    try {
        ostringstream strbuf;
        unsigned int i = 0;
        con.real_connect(MY_DATABASE, MY_HOST, MY_USER, MY_PASSWORD, 3306,
                         0, 60, NULL);
        Query query = con.query();
        query &lt;&lt; MY_QUERY;
        ResUse res = query.use();
        Row row;
        strbuf &lt;&lt; "delete from " &lt;&lt; MY_TABLE &lt;&lt; " where " &lt;&lt; MY_FIELD &lt;&lt;
            " in (";
        //  for UPDATE just replace the above DELETE FROM with UPDATE statement
        for (; row = res.fetch_row(); i++)
            strbuf &lt;&lt; row[0] &lt;&lt; ",";
        if (!i)
            return 0;
        string output(strbuf.str());
        output.erase(output.size() - 1, 1);
        output += ")";
        query.exec(output);
        //cout &lt;&lt; output &lt;&lt; endl;
    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; " " &lt;&lt; con.errnum() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl
            &lt;&lt; "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved
            &lt;&lt; " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }

    return 0;
} </programlisting></blockquote>

			<para>Notice that the row values
			used in the IN clause aren't escaped or
			quoted. This is because row elements are <ulink
			url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1ColData__Tmpl.html">ColData</ulink>
			types, so they have automatic escaping and
			quoting, as appropriate to the type being
			inserted. If you want to disable this feature,
			it's easily done: click the ColData link for
			the details.</para>

			<para>Users of this example should beware that
			one more check is required in order to run this
			query safely: in some extreme cases, the size
			of the query might grow larger than MySQL's
			maximum allowed packet size. This check should
			be added.</para>
		</sect3>
	</sect2>
</sect1>


<?hard-pagebreak?>
<sect1>
	<title id="tquery" xreflabel="template queries">Template
			Queries</title>

	<para>Another powerful feature of MySQL++ is being able
	to set up template queries. These are kind of like C's
	<computeroutput>printf()</computeroutput> facility: you
	give MySQL++ a string containing the fixed parts of the
	query and placeholders for the variable parts, and you can
	later substitute in values into those placeholders.</para>

	<para>The following example demonstrates how to use
	this feature. This is the program you've run a few
	times now if you've worked through all the examples,
	resetdb.cpp:</para>

	<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;

#include &lt;iostream&gt;

using namespace std;

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    mysqlpp::Connection con(mysqlpp::use_exceptions);
    try {
        if (!connect_to_db(argc, argv, con, "")) {
            return 1;
        }
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Connection failed: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return 1;
    }
    
    bool created = false;
    try {
        con.select_db(kpcSampleDatabase);
    }
    catch (mysqlpp::BadQuery &amp;) {
        // Couldn't switch to the sample database, so assume that it
        // doesn't exist and create it.  If that doesn't work, exit
        // with an error.
        if (con.create_db(kpcSampleDatabase)) {
            cerr &lt;&lt; "Failed to create sample database: " &lt;&lt;
                    con.error() &lt;&lt; endl;
            return 1;
        }
        else if (!con.select_db(kpcSampleDatabase)) {
            cerr &lt;&lt; "Failed to select sample database." &lt;&lt; endl;
            return 1;
        }
        else {
            created = true;
        }
    }

    mysqlpp::Query query = con.query(); // create a new query object

    try {
        query.execute("drop table stock");
    }
    catch (mysqlpp::BadQuery&amp;) {
        // ignore any errors
    }

    try {
        // Send the query to create the table and execute it.
        query &lt;&lt; "create table stock  (item char(20) not null, num bigint,"
            &lt;&lt; "weight double, price double, sdate date)";
        query.execute();

        // Set up the template query to insert the data.  The parse
        // call tells the query object that this is a template and
        // not a literal query string.
        query &lt;&lt; "insert into %5:table values (%0q, %1q, %2, %3, %4q)";
        query.parse();

        // This is setting the parameter named table to stock.
        query.def["table"] = "stock";

        // The last parameter "table" is not specified here.  Thus the
        // default value for "table" is used, which is "stock".  Also
        // notice that the first row is a UTF-8 encoded Unicode string!
        // All you have to do to store Unicode data in recent versions
        // of MySQL is use UTF-8 encoding.
        query.execute("Nürnberger Brats", 92, 1.5, 8.79, "2005-03-10");
        query.execute("Pickle Relish", 87, 1.5, 1.75, "1998-09-04");
        query.execute("Hot Mustard", 75, .95, .97, "1998-05-25");
        query.execute("Hotdog Buns", 65, 1.1, 1.1, "1998-04-23");

        if (created) {
            cout &lt;&lt; "Created";
        }
        else {
            cout &lt;&lt; "Reinitialized";
        }
        cout &lt;&lt; " sample database successfully." &lt;&lt; endl;
    }
    catch (mysqlpp::BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return 1;
    }
    catch (mysqlpp::BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl
            &lt;&lt; "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved
            &lt;&lt; " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return 1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return 1;
    }

    return 0;
} </programlisting></blockquote>

	<para>The line just before the call to
	<computeroutput>query.parse()</computeroutput> sets the
	template, and the parse call puts it into effect. From
	that point on, you can re-use this query by calling any
	of several Query member functions that accept query
	template parameters. In this example, we're using
	<computeroutput>Query::execute()</computeroutput>.</para>

	<para>Let's dig into this feature a little deeper.</para>


	<sect2>
		<title>Setting up template queries</title>

		<para>To set up a template query, you simply insert it into
		the Query object, using numbered placeholders wherever you
		want to be able to change the query. Then, you call the
		parse() function to tell the Query object that the query
		string is a template query, and it needs to parse it:</para>

		<programlisting>
    query &lt;&lt; "select (%2:field1, %3:field2) from stock where
            %1:wheref = %q0:what";
    query.parse();</programlisting>

		<para>The format of the placeholder is:</para>

		<programlisting>
    %(modifier)##(:name)(:)</programlisting>

		<para>Where Modifier can be any one of the following:</para>

		<blockquote>
		<informaltable frame="none">
		<tgroup cols="2">
		<colspec colsep="1" rowsep="1"/>
		<tbody>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">%</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Print an actual "%"</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">""</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Don't quote or escape no matter what.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">q</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>This will quote and escape
				the item using the MySQL C API
				function mysql_escape_string()
				if it is a string or char *,
				or another MySQL-specific type
				that needs to be quoted.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">Q</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Quote but don't escape
				based on the same rules as for 'q'. This
				can save a bit of processing time if you
				know the strings will never need
				quoting</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">r</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Always quote and escape
				even if it is a number.</entry>
			</row>
			<row>
				<entry><emphasis role="bold">R</emphasis></entry>
				<entry>Always quote but
				don't escape even if it is
				a number.</entry>
			</row>
		</tbody>
		</tgroup>
		</informaltable>
		</blockquote>

		<para>## represents a number up to two digits. It is the
		order of parameters given to a <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1SQLQueryParms.html">SQLQueryParms</ulink>
		object, starting from 0.</para>

		<para>":name" is for an optional name which aids
		in filling SQLQueryParms. Name can contain any
		alpha-numeric characters or the underscore. If
		you add this, it must start with a letter. If this
		is not the case, add a colon after the name. If
		you need to represent an actual colon after the
		name, follow the name with two colons. The first
		one will end the name and the second one won't
		be processed.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Setting the parameters at execution time</title>

		<para>To specify the parameters when
		you want to execute a query simply
		use <computeroutput>Query::store(const
		SQLString &amp;parm0, [..., const SQLString
		&amp;parm11])</computeroutput>. This
		type of multiple overload also exists for
		<computeroutput>Query::use()</computeroutput> and
		<computeroutput>Query::execute()</computeroutput>.
		'parm0' corresponds to the first parameter,
		etc. You may specify up to 12 parameters. For
		example:</para>

		<programlisting>
    Result res = query.store("Dinner Rolls", "item", "item", "price")</programlisting>

		<para>with the template query provided above
		would produce:</para>

		<programlisting>
    select (item, price) from stock where item = "Dinner Rolls"</programlisting>

		<para>The reason we didn't put the template parameters in
		numeric order...</para>

		<programlisting>
    select (%0:field1, %1:field2) from stock where %2:wheref = %q3:what</programlisting>

		<para>...will become apparent shortly.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Using defaults</title>

		<para>You can also set the parameters one at
		a time by means of class Query's public data
		member def. To change the values of the def,
		simply use the subscript operator. You can
		refer to the parameters either by number or by
		name. The following two examples have the same effect:</para>

		<programlisting>
    query.def[0] = "Dinner Rolls"; 
    query.def[1] = "item"; 
    query.def[2] = "item"; 
    query.def[3] = "price";</programlisting>

		<para>and</para>

		<programlisting>
    query.def["what"] = "Dinner Rolls"; 
    query.def["wheref"] = "item"; 
    query.def["field1"] = "item"; 
    query.def["field2"] = "price";</programlisting>

		<para>Once all the parameters are set simply
		execute as you would have executed the query
		before you knew about template queries:</para>

		<programlisting>
    Result res = query.store()</programlisting>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Combining the two</title>

		<para>You can also combine the use of
		setting the parameters at execution time and
		setting them via the def object by calling
		<computeroutput>Query::store()</computeroutput>
		(or <computeroutput>use()</computeroutput>
		or <computeroutput>execute()</computeroutput>)
		without passing the full number of parameters
		that the template supports:</para>

		<programlisting>
    query.def["field1"] = "item"; 
    query.def["field2"] = "price"; 
    Result res1 = query.store("Hamburger Buns", "item"); 
    Result res2 = query.store(1.25, "price"); </programlisting>

		<para>Would store the query:</para>

		<programlisting>
    select (item, price) from stock where item = "Hamburger Buns" </programlisting>

		<para>for res1 and</para>

		<programlisting>
    select (item, price) from stock where price = 1.25 </programlisting>

		<para>for res2.</para>

		<para>Now you see why we ordered the placeholders
		in the template above as we did: we used positions
		0 and 1 for the ones we want to change frequently,
		and used 2 and 3 for the parameters that seldom
		change.</para>

		<para>One thing to watch out for, however,
		is that <computeroutput>Query::store(const
		char* q)</computeroutput> is also defined for
		executing the query q. Therefore, when you call
		<computeroutput>Query::store()</computeroutput>
		(or <computeroutput>use()</computeroutput>,
		or <computeroutput>execute()</computeroutput>)
		with only one item and that item is a const
		char*, you need to explicitly convert it into
		a SQLString to get the right overload:</para>

		<programlisting>
    Result res = query.store(SQLString("Hamburger Buns")); </programlisting>
		<para></para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Error Handling</title>

		<para>If for some reason you did not specify all
		the parameters when executing the query and the
		remaining parameters do not have their values
		set via def, the query object will throw a <ulink
		url="../../refman/html/classmysqlpp_1_1SQLQueryNEParms.html">SQLQueryNEParms</ulink>
		object. If this happens, you
		can get an explanation of what
		happened by checking the value of
		<computeroutput>SQLQueryNEParms::string</computeroutput>,
		like so:</para>

		<programlisting>
    query.def["field1"] = "item"; 
    query.def["field2"] = "price"; 
    Result res = query.store(1.25); </programlisting>

		<para>This would throw
		<computeroutput>SQLQueryNEParms</computeroutput>
		because the wheref is not specified.</para>

		<para>In theory, this exception should never be
		thrown. If the exception is thrown it probably
		a logic error in your program.</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>


<?hard-pagebreak?>
<sect1>
	<title id="ssqls" xreflabel="Specialized SQL Structures"
			>Specialized SQL Structures</title>

	<para>The Specialized SQL Structure (SSQLS) feature lets you
	easily define C++ structures that match the form of your SQL
	tables. Because of the extra functionality that this feature
	builds into these structures, MySQL++ can populate them
	automatically when retrieving data from the database; with
	queries returning many records, you can ask MySQL++ to populate
	an STL container of your SSQLS records with the results. When
	updating the database, MySQL++ can use SSQLS structures to match
	existing data, and it can insert SSQLS structures directly into
	the database.</para>

	<para>You define an SSQLS using one of several macros. (These
	are in the file custom.h, and in the file that it includes,
	custom-macros.h.) There are a bunch of different macros, for
	different purposes. The following sections will discuss each
	macro type separately, beginning with the easiest and most
	generally useful.</para>


	<sect2>
		<title>sql_create</title>

		<para>This is the most basic sort of SSQLS declaration:</para>

		<programlisting>
    sql_create_5(stock, 0, 0,     
            string, item,
            int, num,                  
            double, weight,  
            double, price,  
            mysqlpp::Date, date)</programlisting>

		<para>This creates a C++ structure called 'stock'
		containing five member variables, along with some
		constructors and other member functions useful with
		MySQL++.</para>

		<para>One of the generated constructors takes a reference
		to a mysqlpp::Row object, allowing you to easily populate
		a vector of stocks like so:</para>

		<programlisting>
    vector&lt;stock&gt; result; 
    query.storein(result);</programlisting>

		<para>That's all there is to it. The only requirements
		are that the table structure be compatible with the
		SSQLS's member variables, and that the fields are in
		the same order.</para>

		<para>The general format of this set of macros is:</para>

		<programlisting>
    sql_create_#(NAME, KEYS, INITPARMS, TYPE1, ITEM1, ... TYPE#, ITEM#)</programlisting>

		<para>Where # is the number of member variables,
		NAME is the name of the structure you wish to create,
		TYPE<emphasis>x</emphasis> is the type name for a
		member variable, and ITEM<emphasis>x</emphasis> is that
		variable's name.</para>

		<para>The KEYS and INITPARMS arguments can always be zero,
		to keep things simple. We will discuss what happens if
		you use different values in the next few sections.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>sql_create with Compare</title>

		<para>SSQLS structures can also have member functions that
		allow you to compare one structure to another. You simply
		change the first 0 in the previous example (KEYS) to a
		higher value. If this number is N, then two structures
		are considered equal if the first N members of each
		are equal.</para>

		<para>For example:</para>

		<programlisting>
    sql_create_5(stock, 1, 0,     
            string, item,
            int, num,                  
            double, weight,  
            double, price,  
            mysqlpp::Date, date)</programlisting>

		<para>Here we are saying that the 'item' field is a kind
		of key field: it is always unique between any two 'stock'
		items, so if two stock records have equal item values,
		they are the same stock item.</para>

		<para>That change adds the following members to the
		SSQLS:</para>

		<programlisting>
    struct stock {
      ...  
      stock (const std::string &amp;p1); 
      set (const std::string &amp;p1); 
      bool operator == (const stock &amp;other) const;  
      bool operator != (const stock &amp;other) const;   
      bool operator &gt; (const stock &amp;other) const;   
      bool operator &lt; (const stock &amp;other) const;   
      bool operator &gt;= (const stock &amp;other) const;   
      bool operator &lt;= (const stock &amp;other) const;   
      int cmp (const stock &amp;other) const;  
      int compare (const stock &amp;other) const;  
    }  
      
    int compare (const stock &amp;x, const stock &amp;y);</programlisting>

		<para>The global
		<computeroutput>compare()</computeroutput>
		function compares x to y and returns &lt;0 if
		x &lt; y, 0 if x = y, and &gt;0 if x &gt; y.
		<computeroutput>stock::cmp()</computeroutput> and
		<computeroutput>stock::compare()</computeroutput>
		are the same thing as <computeroutput>compare(*this,
		other)</computeroutput>.</para>

		<para>The additional constructor initializes the key
		fields of the structure and leaves the other member
		variables undefined. This is useful for creating temporary
		objects to use for comparisons like <computeroutput>x
		&lt;= stock("Hotdog")</computeroutput>.</para>

		<para>Because stock is now less-than-comparable you
		can store the query results in an STL associative
		container:</para>

		<programlisting>
    std::set&lt;stock&gt; result;   
    query.storein(result);</programlisting>

		<para>And you can now use it like any other set:</para>

		<programlisting>
    cout &lt;&lt; result.lower_bound(stock("Hamburger"))-&gt;item &lt;&lt; endl;</programlisting>

		<para>This will return the first item that begins with
		"Hamburger".</para>

		<para>You can also use it will any STL algorithm that
		require the values to be less-than-comparable.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>sql_create with Additional Initializers</title>

		<para>If third parameter for this macro (INITPARMS) is
		nonzero, the SSQLS will have two additional members
		functions that make it easier to initialize the
		structure's data members. For example:</para>

		<programlisting>
    sql_create_5(stock, 1, 5,   
            string, item,
            int, num,                  
            double, weight,  
            double, price,  
            mysqlpp::Date, date)</programlisting>

		<para>will add these functions to the structure relative to
		that in the previous example:</para>

		<programlisting>
    struct stock {   
      ...  
      stock(const string&amp;, const int&amp;, const double&amp;,  
            const double&amp;, const mysqlpp::Date&amp;);  
      set(const string&amp;, const int&amp;, const double&amp;,  
          const double&amp;, const mysqlpp::Date&amp;);  
    }</programlisting>

		<para>There is one trick with this: because each SSQLS
		has at least one other constructor besides the one
		defined by this feature, not every logical value for
		INITPARMS results in working code. A simple example is
		setting KEYS and INITPARMS to the same value: you get
		two identical constructor definitions, so the compiler
		refuses to compile the code. If you are getting compiler
		errors having to do with duplicate definitions, try
		changing this value to zero.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Additional Features of Specialized SQL Structures</title>
		
		<para>Up to this point, we haven't been using
		all of the features in the SSQLS structures
		we've been generating. We could have used the
		<computeroutput>sql_create_basic_*</computeroutput>
		macros instead, which would have worked just as well
		for what we've seen so far, and the generated code would
		have been smaller.</para>

		<para>Why is it worth ignoring the "basic" variants of
		these macros, then? Consider this:</para>

		<programlisting>
    query.insert(s);</programlisting>

		<para>This does exactly what you think it does:
		it inserts 's' into the database. This is possible
		because a standard SSQLS has functions that the
		query object can call to get the list of fields
		and such, which it uses to build an insert query.
		<computeroutput>query::update()</computeroutput> and
		<computeroutput>query::replace()</computeroutput> also
		rely on this SSQLS feature. A basic SSQLS lacks these
		functions.</para>

		<para>Another feature of standard SSQLSes you might find
		a use for is changing the table name used in queries. By
		default, the table in the MySQL database is assumed to
		have the same name as the SSQLS structure type. But if
		this is inconvenient, you can globally change the table
		name used in queries like this:</para>

		<programlisting>
    stock::table() = "MyStockData";</programlisting>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Harnessing SSQLS Internals</title>

		<para>Continuing the discussion in the
		previous section, there is a further set of
		methods that the non-"basic" versions of the
		<computeroutput>sql_create</computeroutput> macros
		define for each SSQLS. These methods are mostly for
		use within the library, but some of them are useful
		enough that you might want to harness them for your
		own ends. Here is some pseudocode showing how the
		most useful of these methods would be defined for the
		<computeroutput>stock</computeroutput> structure used
		in all the <computeroutput>custom*.cpp</computeroutput>
		examples:</para>

		<blockquote><programlisting>
// Basic form
template &lt;class Manip&gt;   
stock_value_list&lt;Manip&gt; value_list(cchar *d = &#34;,&#34;,
    Manip m = mysqlpp::quote) const;  

template &lt;class Manip&gt;   
stock_field_list&lt;Manip&gt; field_list(cchar *d = &#34;,&#34;,   
    Manip m = mysqlpp::do_nothing) const;  

template &lt;class Manip&gt;   
stock_equal_list&lt;Manip&gt; equal_list(cchar *d = &#34;,&#34;,
    cchar *e = &#34; = &#34;, Manip m = mysqlpp::quote) const;  


// Boolean argument form
template &lt;class Manip&gt;
stock_cus_value_list&lt;Manip&gt; value_list([cchar *d, [Manip m,] ]   
    bool i1, bool i2 = false, ... , bool i5 = false) const;  

// List form  
template &lt;class Manip&gt;
stock_cus_value_list&lt;Manip&gt; value_list([cchar *d, [Manip m,] ]  
    stock_enum i1, stock_enum i2 = stock_NULL, ...,
    stock_enum i5 = stock_NULL) const;  

// Vector form  
template &lt;class Manip&gt;
stock_cus_value_list&lt;Manip&gt; value_list([cchar *d, [Manip m,] ]  
    vector&lt;bool&gt; *i) const;  

...Plus the obvious equivalents for field_list() and equal_list()</programlisting></blockquote>

		<para>Rather than try to learn what all of these methods
		do at once, let's ease into the subject. Consider this
		code:</para>

		<blockquote><programlisting>
stock s("Dinner Rolls", 75, 0.95, 0.97, "1998-05-25");   
cout &lt;&lt; "Value list: " &lt;&lt; s.comma_list() &lt;&lt; endl;  
cout &lt;&lt; "Field list: " &lt;&lt; s.field_list() &lt;&lt; endl;  
cout &lt;&lt; "Equal list: " &lt;&lt; s.equal_list() &lt;&lt; endl;</programlisting></blockquote>

		<para>That would produce something like:</para>

		<blockquote><programlisting>
Value list: 'Dinner Rolls',75,0.95,0.97,'1998-05-25'   
Field list: item,num,weight,price,date  
Equal list: item = 'Dinner Rolls',num = 75,weight = 0.95, price = 0.97,date = '1998-05-25'</programlisting></blockquote>

		<para>That is, a "value list" is a list of data member
		values within a particular SSQLS instance, a "field list"
		is a list of the fields (columns) within that SSQLS,
		and an "equal list" is a list in the form of an SQL
		equals clause.</para>
		
		<para>Just knowing that much, it
		shouldn't surprise you to learn that
		<computeroutput>Query::insert()</computeroutput> is
		implemented more or less like this:</para>

		<blockquote><programlisting>
*this &lt;&lt; "INSERT INTO " &lt;&lt; v.table() &lt;&lt; " (" &lt;&lt; v.field_list() &lt;&lt;
        ") VALUES (" &lt;&lt; v.value_list() &lt;&lt; ")";</programlisting></blockquote>

		<para>where 'v' is the SSQLS you're asking the
		Query object to insert into the database.</para>

		<para>Now let's look at a complete example,
		which uses one of the more complicated forms of
		<computeroutput>equal_list()</computeroutput>. This
		example builds a query with fewer hard-coded strings
		than the most obvious technique requires, which
		makes it more robust in the face of change. Here is
		examples/custom5.cpp:</para>

		<blockquote><programlisting>
#include "util.h"

#include &lt;mysql++.h&gt;
#include &lt;custom.h&gt;

#include &lt;iostream&gt;
#include &lt;iomanip&gt;
#include &lt;vector&gt;

using namespace std;
using namespace mysqlpp;

sql_create_5(stock,
             1, 5,
             string, item,
             longlong, num,
             double, weight,
             double, price,
             Date, sdate)

int
main(int argc, char *argv[])
{
    try {
        Connection con(use_exceptions);
        if (!connect_to_db(argc, argv, con)) {
            return 1;
        }

        // Get all the rows in the stock table.
        Query query = con.query();
        query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock";
        vector&lt;stock&gt; res;
        query.storein(res);

        if (res.size() &gt; 0) {
            // Build a select query using the data from the first row
            // returned by our previous query.
            query.reset();
            query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock where " &lt;&lt;
                res[0].equal_list(" and ", stock_weight, stock_price);

            // Display the finished query.
            cout &lt;&lt; "Custom query:\n" &lt;&lt; query.preview() &lt;&lt; endl;
        }

        return 0;
    }
    catch (BadQuery&amp; er) {
        // Handle any connection or query errors
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (BadConversion&amp; er) {
        // Handle bad conversions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; "\"." &lt;&lt; endl &lt;&lt;
                "retrieved data size: " &lt;&lt; er.retrieved &lt;&lt;
                " actual data size: " &lt;&lt; er.actual_size &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
    catch (exception&amp; er) {
        // Catch-all for any other standard C++ exceptions
        cerr &lt;&lt; "Error: " &lt;&lt; er.what() &lt;&lt; endl;
        return -1;
    }
}</programlisting></blockquote>

		<para>This example uses the list form of
		<computeroutput>equal_list()</computeroutput>. The
		arguments <computeroutput>stock_weight</computeroutput>
		and <computeroutput>stock_price</computeroutput>
		are enum values equal to the position of these columns
		within the <computeroutput>stock</computeroutput> table.
		<computeroutput>sql_create_</computeroutput><emphasis>x</emphasis>
		generates this enum for you automatically.</para>

		<para>The boolean argument form of that
		<computeroutput>equal_list()</computeroutput> call would
		look like this:</para>

		<blockquote><programlisting>
query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock where " &lt;&lt;
        res[0].equal_list(" and ", false, false, true, true, false);</programlisting></blockquote>

		<para>It's a little more verbose, as you can
		see. And if you want to get really complicated,
		use the vector form:</para>

		<blockquote><programlisting>
vector&lt;bool&gt; v(5, false);
v[stock_weight] = true;
v[stock_price] = true;
query &lt;&lt; "select * from stock where " &lt;&lt;
        res[0].equal_list(" and ", v);</programlisting></blockquote>

		<para>This form makes the most sense if you are
		building many other queries, and so can re-use that
		vector object.</para>

		<para>Many of these methods accept manipulators and custom
		delimiters. The defaults are suitable for building SQL
		queries, but if you're using these methods in a different
		context, you may need to override these defaults. For
		instance, you could use these methods to dump data to a
		text file using different delimiters and quoting rules
		than SQL.</para>

		<para>At this point, we've seen all the major aspects
		of the SSQLS feature. The final sections of this chapter
		look at some of the peripheral aspects.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Alternate Creation Methods</title>

		<para>If for some reason you want your SSQLS data members to
		have different names than used in the MySQL database, you can do
		so like this:</para>

		<programlisting>
    sql_create_c_names_5(stock, 1, 5,        
            string, item, "item",
            int, num, "quantity",  
            double, weight, "weight",  
            double, price, "price"  
            mysqlpp::Date, date, "shipment")</programlisting>

		<para>If you want your SSQLS to have its data members
		in a different order from those in the MySQL table,
		you can do it like this:</para>

		<programlisting>
    sql_create_c_order_5(stock, 2, 5,   
            mysqlpp::Date, date, 5,
            double, price, 4,   
            string, item, 1,    
            int, num, 2,   
            double, weight, 3)</programlisting>

		<para>You can combine the custom names and custom ordering like
		this:</para>

		<programlisting>
    sql_create_complete_5(stock, 2, 5,   
            mysqlpp::date, date, "shipment", 5,
            double, price, "price", 4,
            string, item, "item", 1,
            int, num, "quantity", 2,
            double, weight, "weight", 3)</programlisting>

		<para>All three of these macro types have "basic"
		variants that work the same way. Again, basic SSQLSes
		lack the features necessary for automatic insert, update
		and replace query creation.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Expanding SSQLS Macros</title>

		<para>If you ever need to see the code that a given SSQLS
		declaration expands out to, use the utility
		<computeroutput>doc/ssqls-pretty</computeroutput>, like so:</para>

		<programlisting>
    ssqls-pretty &lt; myprog.cpp |less</programlisting>

		<para>This locates the first SSQLS declaration in that
		file and uses the C++ preprocessor to expand that
		macro. You may have to change the script to tell it
		where your MySQL++ header files are.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Extending the SSQLS Mechanism</title>

		<para>The SSQLS headers &mdash; custom.h and
		custom-macros.h &mdash; are automatically generated
		by the Perl script custom.pl. Although it is possible
		to change this script to get additional functionality,
		it's usually better to do that through inheritance.</para>
		
		<para>A regular user may find it helpful to change the the
		limit on the maximum number of SSQLS data members allowed.
		It's 25 out of the box. A smaller value may speed up
		compile time, or you may require a higher value because
		you have more complex tables than that. Simply change the
		<computeroutput>max_data_members</computeroutput> variable
		at the top of custom.pl and say 'make'. The limit for
		Visual C++ is 31, according to one report. There doesn't
		seem to be a practical limit with GCC 3.3 at least: I
		set the limit to 100 and the only thing that happened is
		that custom-macros.h went from 1.3 MB to 18 MB and the
		build time for examples/custom.* got a lot longer.</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>


<?hard-pagebreak?>
<sect1>
	<title id="unicode" xreflabel="Using Unicode with MySQL++">Using
			Unicode with MySQL++</title>

	<sect2>
		<title>A Short History of Unicode</title>
		<subtitle>...with a focus on relevance to MySQL++</subtitle>

		<para>In the old days, computer operating systems
		only dealt with 8-bit character sets. This only gives
		you 256 possible characters, but the modern Western
		languages have more than that by themselves. Add in
		all the other lanauges of the world, plus the various
		symbols people use, and you have a real mess! Since no
		standards body held sway over things like international
		character encoding in the early days of computing, many
		different character sets were invented. These character
		sets weren't even standardized between operating systems,
		so heaven help you if you needed to move localized Greek
		text on a Windows machine to a Russian Macintosh! The only
		way we got any international communication done at all
		was to build standards on the common 7-bit ASCII subset.
		Either people used approximations like a plain "c" instead
		of the French "&ccedil;", or they invented things like
		HTML entities ("&amp;ccedil;" in this case) to encode
		these additional characters using only 7-bit ASCII.</para>

		<para>Unicode solves this problem. It encodes every
		character in the world, using up to 4 bytes per
		character. The subset covering the most economically
		valuable cases takes two bytes per character, so most
		Unicode-aware programs limit themselves to this set,
		for efficiency.</para>

		<para>Unfortunately, Unicode came about 20 years
		too late for Unix and C. Converting the Unix
		system call interface to Unicode would break all
		existing programs. The ISO lashed a wide character <ulink
		url="http://www.jargon.net/jargonfile/s/sidecar.html">sidecar</ulink>
		onto C in 1995, but in common practice C is still tied
		to 8-bit characters.</para>

		<para>As Unicode began to take off in the early 1990s,
		it became clear that some sort of accommodation
		with Unicode was needed in legacy systems like
		Unix and C. During the development of the <ulink
		url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plan_9_from_Bell_Labs">Plan
		9</ulink> operating system (a kind
		of successor to Unix) Ken Thompson <ulink
		url="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/ucs/utf-8-history.txt">invented</ulink>
		the <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UTF-8">UTF-8
		encoding</ulink>. Since UTF-8 is a superset of 7-bit
		ASCII, many programs that deal in text actually get by
		okay without any explicit support for UTF-8.</para>

		<para>The MySQL database server comes out of the
		Unix/C tradition, so it only supports 8-bit characters
		natively. UTF-8 data is compatible with C strings, so all
		versions of MySQL could store UTF-8 data, but sometimes
		the database actually needs to understand the data.
		When sorting, for instance. To support this, explicit
		UTF-8 support was added to MySQL in version 4.1.</para>

		<para>Because MySQL++ does not need to know
		anything about the flowing through it, it
		doesn't have explicit UTF-8 support.  C++'s
		<computeroutput>std::string</computeroutput> stores
		UTF-8 data just fine. But, your program probably
		<emphasis>does</emphasis> care about the data coming
		from MySQL++. The remainder of this chapter covers the
		choices you have for dealing with UTF-8 encoded Unicode
		data.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Unicode and Unix</title>

		<para>Modern Unices support UTF-8 natively. Red Hat Linux,
		for instance, has had system-wide UTF-8 support since
		version 8. This continues in the commercial and Fedora
		forks of Red Hat Linux, of course.</para>

		<para>On such a Unix, the terminal I/O code understands
		UTF-8 encoded data, so your program doesn't require any
		special code to correctly display a UTF-8 string. If you
		aren't sure whether your system supports UTF-8 natively,
		just run the simple1 example: if the first item has
		two high-ASCII characters in place of the "&uuml;" in
		"N&uuml;rnberger Brats", you know it's not handling
		UTF-8.</para>

		<para>If your Unix doesn't support UTF-8 natively,
		it likely doesn't support any form of Unicode at all,
		for the historical reasons I gave above. Therefore,
		you will have to convert the UTF-8 data to the
		local 8-bit character set. The standard Unix
		function <computeroutput>iconv()</computeroutput>
		can help here. If your system doesn't have the
		<computeroutput>iconv()</computeroutput> facility, there
		is <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/libiconv/">a
		free implementation</ulink> available from the GNU
		Project. Another library you might check out is IBM's
		<ulink url="http://icu.sourceforge.net/">ICU</ulink>. This
		is rather heavy-weight, so if you just need basic
		conversions, <computeroutput>iconv()</computeroutput>
		should suffice.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>Unicode and Win32</title>

		<para>Each Win32 API function that takes
		a string actually has two two versions. One
		version supports only 1-byte "ANSI" characters (a
		superset of ASCII), so they end in 'A'. Win32 also
		supports the 2-byte subset of Unicode called <ulink
		url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UCS-2">UCS-2</ulink>.
		Some call these "wide" characters, so the other
		set of functions end in 'W'. The <computeroutput><ulink
		url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/en-us/winui/winui/windowsuserinterface/windowing/dialogboxes/dialogboxreference/dialogboxfunctions/messagebox.asp">MessageBox</ulink>()</computeroutput>
		API, for instance, is actually a macro,
		not a real function. If you define the
		<computeroutput>UNICODE</computeroutput>
		macro when building your program, the
		<computeroutput>MessageBox()</computeroutput>
		macro evaluates to
		<computeroutput>MessageBoxW()</computeroutput>; otherwise,
		to <computeroutput>MessageBoxA()</computeroutput>.</para>

		<para>Since MySQL uses UTF-8 and Win32 uses UCS-2,
		you must convert data going between the Win32
		API and MySQL++. Since there's no point in trying
		for portability &mdash; no other OS I'm aware of
		uses UCS-2 &mdash; you might as well use native
		Win32 functions for doing this translation. The following code
		is distilled from <computeroutput>utf8_to_win32_ansi()</computeroutput>
		in <computeroutput>examples/util.cpp</computeroutput>:</para>

		<blockquote><programlisting>
void utf8_to_win32_ansi(const char* utf8_str, char* ansi_str, int ansi_len)
{
    wchar_t ucs2_buf[100];
    static const int ub_chars = sizeof(ucs2_buf) / sizeof(ucs2_buf[0]);

    MultiByteToWideChar(CP_UTF8, 0, utf8_str, -1, ucs2_buf, ub_chars);
    CPINFOEX cpi;
    GetCPInfoEx(CP_OEMCP, 0, &amp;cpi);
    WideCharToMultiByte(cpi.CodePage, 0, ucs2_buf, -1,
            ansi_str, ansi_len, 0, 0);
}</programlisting></blockquote>

		<para>To see this in action, uncomment
		"<computeroutput>#define USE_WIN32_UCS2</computeroutput>"
		at the top of util.cpp, build the example programs, and
		run simple1 in a console window (a.k.a. "DOS box"). The
		first item should be "N&uuml;rnberger Brats". If not,
		see the last paragraph in this section.</para>

		<para><computeroutput>utf8_to_win32_ansi()</computeroutput>
		converts <computeroutput>utf8_str</computeroutput>
		from UTF-8 to UCS-2, and from there to the local <ulink
		url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/intl/unicode_81rn.asp">code
		page</ulink>. "Waitaminnit," you shout! "I thought we
		were trying to get away from the problem of local code
		pages!" The console is one of the few Win32 facilities
		that doesn't support UCS-2 by default. It can be <ulink
		url="http://www.answers.com/topic/win32-console">put
		into UCS-2 mode</ulink>, but that seems like more
		work than we'd like to go to in a portable example
		program.  Since the default code page in most versions
		of Windows includes the "&uuml;" character used in the
		sample database, this conversion works out fine for our
		purposes.</para>
		
		<para>If your program is using the GUI to display
		text, you don't need the second conversion. Prove
		this to yourself by adding the following to
		<computeroutput>utf8_to_win32_ansi()</computeroutput>
		after the
		<computeroutput>MultiByteToWideChar()</computeroutput>
		call:</para>

		<programlisting>
	MessageBox(0, ucs2_buf, "UCS-2 version of Item", MB_OK);</programlisting>

		<para>All of this assumes you're using Windows NT or one
		of its direct descendants: Windows 2000, Windows XP,
		Windows 2003 Server, and someday "Longhorn". Windows
		95/98/ME and Windows CE do not support UCS-2. They
		still have the 'W' APIs for compatibility, but they
		just smash the data down to 8-bit and call the 'A'
		version for you.</para>
	</sect2>


	<sect2>
		<title>For More Information</title>
			<para>The <ulink
			url="http://www.unicode.org/faq/">Unicode
			FAQs</ulink> page has copious information on
			this complex topic.</para>

			<para>When it comes to Unix
			and UTF-8 specific items, the <ulink
			url="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/~mgk25/unicode.html">UTF-8
			and Unicode FAQ for Unix/Linux</ulink> is a
			quicker way to find basic information.</para>
		</sect2>
</sect1>


<?hard-pagebreak?>
<sect1>
	<title>Licensing</title>

	<para>The primary copyright holders on MySQL++ are Kevin Atkinson
	(1998), MySQL AB (1999 through 2001) and Educational Technology
	Resources, Inc. (2004 through the date of this writing).</para>
	
	<para>MySQL++ is released under the GNU Lesser General Public
	License (LGPL), reproduced below.</para>

	<para>This license basically states that you are free to use,
	distribute and modify these works, whether for personal or
	commercial purposes, as long as you grant the same rights to
	those you distribute the works to, whether you changed them or
	not. See the licenses below for full details.</para>


<sect2>
	<title>GNU Lesser General Public License</title>
	<subtitle>Version 2.1, February 1999</subtitle>

	<para>Copyright (C) 1991, 1999 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
	59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA	02111-1307  USA Everyone
	is permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this
	license document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>

	<para>[This is the first released version of the Lesser GPL.
	It also counts as the successor of the GNU Library Public License,
	version 2, hence the version number 2.1.]</para>

	<sect3>
		<title>Preamble</title>

		<para>The licenses for most software are designed to take
		away your freedom to share and change it.  By contrast,
		the GNU General Public Licenses are intended to guarantee
		your freedom to share and change free software--to make
		sure the software is free for all its users.</para>

		<para>This license, the Lesser General Public License,
		applies to some specially designated software
		packages--typically libraries--of the Free Software
		Foundation and other authors who decide to use it.  You
		can use it too, but we suggest you first think carefully
		about whether this license or the ordinary General Public
		License is the better strategy to use in any particular
		case, based on the explanations below.</para>

		<para>When we speak of free software, we are referring to
		freedom of use, not price.  Our General Public Licenses
		are designed to make sure that you have the freedom to
		distribute copies of free software (and charge for this
		service if you wish); that you receive source code or can
		get it if you want it; that you can change the software
		and use pieces of it in new free programs; and that you
		are informed that you can do these things.</para>

		<para>To protect your rights, we need to make restrictions
		that forbid distributors to deny you these rights or to
		ask you to surrender these rights.  These restrictions
		translate to certain responsibilities for you if you
		distribute copies of the library or if you modify
		it.</para>

		<para>For example, if you distribute copies of the
		library, whether gratis or for a fee, you must give the
		recipients all the rights that we gave you.  You must make
		sure that they, too, receive or can get the source code.
		If you link other code with the library, you must provide
		complete object files to the recipients, so that they
		can relink them with the library after making changes
		to the library and recompiling it.  And you must show
		them these terms so they know their rights.</para>

		<para>We protect your rights with a two-step method:
		(1) we copyright the library, and (2) we offer you
		this license, which gives you legal permission to copy,
		distribute and/or modify the library.</para>

		<para>To protect each distributor, we want to make it very
		clear that there is no warranty for the free library.
		Also, if the library is modified by someone else and
		passed on, the recipients should know that what they
		have is not the original version, so that the original
		author's reputation will not be affected by problems
		that might be introduced by others.</para>

		<para>Finally, software patents pose a constant threat to
		the existence of any free program.  We wish to make sure
		that a company cannot effectively restrict the users of
		a free program by obtaining a restrictive license from
		a patent holder.  Therefore, we insist that any patent
		license obtained for a version of the library must be
		consistent with the full freedom of use specified in
		this license.</para>

		<para>Most GNU software, including some libraries,
		is covered by the ordinary GNU General Public License.
		This license, the GNU Lesser General Public License,
		applies to certain designated libraries, and is quite
		different from the ordinary General Public License.  We
		use this license for certain libraries in order to permit
		linking those libraries into non-free programs.</para>

		<para>When a program is linked with a library, whether
		statically or using a shared library, the combination of
		the two is legally speaking a combined work, a derivative
		of the original library.  The ordinary General Public
		License therefore permits such linking only if the entire
		combination fits its criteria of freedom.  The Lesser
		General Public License permits more lax criteria for
		linking other code with the library.</para>

		<para>We call this license the "Lesser" General Public
		License because it does Less to protect the user's
		freedom than the ordinary General Public License.
		It also provides other free software developers Less
		of an advantage over competing non-free programs.
		These disadvantages are the reason we use the ordinary
		General Public License for many libraries.  However,
		the Lesser license provides advantages in certain special
		circumstances.</para>

		<para>For example, on rare occasions, there may be a
		special need to encourage the widest possible use of a
		certain library, so that it becomes a de-facto standard.
		To achieve this, non-free programs must be allowed to use
		the library.  A more frequent case is that a free library
		does the same job as widely used non-free libraries.
		In this case, there is little to gain by limiting the
		free library to free software only, so we use the Lesser
		General Public License.</para>

		<para>In other cases, permission to use a particular
		library in non-free programs enables a greater number of
		people to use a large body of free software.  For example,
		permission to use the GNU C Library in non-free programs
		enables many more people to use the whole GNU operating
		system, as well as its variant, the GNU/Linux operating
		system.</para>

		<para>Although the Lesser General Public License is Less
		protective of the users' freedom, it does ensure that
		the user of a program that is linked with the Library
		has the freedom and the wherewithal to run that program
		using a modified version of the Library.</para>

		<para>The precise terms and conditions for copying,
		distribution and modification follow.  Pay close attention
		to the difference between a "work based on the library"
		and a "work that uses the library".  The former contains
		code derived from the library, whereas the latter must
		be combined with the library in order to run.</para>
	</sect3>


	<sect3>
		<title>GNU LESSER GENERAL PUBLIC LICENSE</title>
		<subtitle>TERMS AND CONDITIONS FOR COPYING, DISTRIBUTION AND
			MODIFICATION</subtitle>

		<para>0. This License Agreement applies to any software
		library or other program which contains a notice placed
		by the copyright holder or other authorized party saying
		it may be distributed under the terms of this Lesser
		General Public License (also called "this License").
		Each licensee is addressed as "you".</para>

		<para>A "library" means a collection of software functions
		and/or data prepared so as to be conveniently linked with
		application programs (which use some of those functions
		and data) to form executables.</para>

		<para>The "Library", below, refers to any such software
		library or work which has been distributed under these
		terms.	A "work based on the Library" means either the
		Library or any derivative work under copyright law: that
		is to say, a work containing the Library or a portion
		of it, either verbatim or with modifications and/or
		translated straightforwardly into another language.
		(Hereinafter, translation is included without limitation
		in the term "modification".)</para>

		<para>"Source code" for a work means the preferred form of
		the work for making modifications to it.  For a library,
		complete source code means all the source code for all
		modules it contains, plus any associated interface
		definition files, plus the scripts used to control
		compilation and installation of the library.</para>

		<para>Activities other than copying, distribution and
		modification are not covered by this License; they are
		outside its scope.  The act of running a program using
		the Library is not restricted, and output from such a
		program is covered only if its contents constitute a
		work based on the Library (independent of the use of
		the Library in a tool for writing it).	Whether that
		is true depends on what the Library does and what the
		program that uses the Library does.</para>

		<para>1. You may copy and distribute verbatim copies
		of the Library's complete source code as you receive
		it, in any medium, provided that you conspicuously
		and appropriately publish on each copy an appropriate
		copyright notice and disclaimer of warranty; keep intact
		all the notices that refer to this License and to the
		absence of any warranty; and distribute a copy of this
		License along with the Library.</para>

		<para>You may charge a fee for the physical act of
		transferring a copy, and you may at your option offer
		warranty protection in exchange for a fee.</para>

		<para>2. You may modify your copy or copies of the Library
		or any portion of it, thus forming a work based on the
		Library, and copy and distribute such modifications or
		work under the terms of Section 1 above, provided that
		you also meet all of these conditions:</para>

		<blockquote>
			<para>a) The modified work must itself be a
			software library.</para>

			<para>b) You must cause the files modified to
			carry prominent notices stating that you changed
			the files and the date of any change.</para>

			<para>c) You must cause the whole of the work
			to be licensed at no charge to all third parties
			under the terms of this License.</para>

			<para>d) If a facility in the modified Library
			refers to a function or a table of data to
			be supplied by an application program that
			uses the facility, other than as an argument
			passed when the facility is invoked, then you
			must make a good faith effort to ensure that,
			in the event an application does not supply such
			function or table, the facility still operates,
			and performs whatever part of its purpose remains
			meaningful.</para>

			<para>(For example, a function in a library
			to compute square roots has a purpose that
			is entirely well-defined independent of the
			application.  Therefore, Subsection 2d requires
			that any application-supplied function or table
			used by this function must be optional: if the
			application does not supply it, the square root
			function must still compute square roots.)</para>
		</blockquote>

		<para>These requirements apply to the modified work as
		a whole.  If identifiable sections of that work are not
		derived from the Library, and can be reasonably considered
		independent and separate works in themselves, then this
		License, and its terms, do not apply to those sections
		when you distribute them as separate works.  But when you
		distribute the same sections as part of a whole which is a
		work based on the Library, the distribution of the whole
		must be on the terms of this License, whose permissions
		for other licensees extend to the entire whole, and thus
		to each and every part regardless of who wrote it.</para>

		<para>Thus, it is not the intent of this section to claim
		rights or contest your rights to work written entirely
		by you; rather, the intent is to exercise the right to
		control the distribution of derivative or collective
		works based on the Library.</para>

		<para>In addition, mere aggregation of another work
		not based on the Library with the Library (or with a
		work based on the Library) on a volume of a storage or
		distribution medium does not bring the other work under
		the scope of this License.</para>

		<para>3. You may opt to apply the terms of the ordinary
		GNU General Public License instead of this License to a
		given copy of the Library.  To do this, you must alter
		all the notices that refer to this License, so that
		they refer to the ordinary GNU General Public License,
		version 2, instead of to this License.	(If a newer
		version than version 2 of the ordinary GNU General Public
		License has appeared, then you can specify that version
		instead if you wish.)  Do not make any other change in
		these notices.</para>

		<para>Once this change is made in a given copy, it is
		irreversible for that copy, so the ordinary GNU General
		Public License applies to all subsequent copies and
		derivative works made from that copy.</para>

		<para>This option is useful when you wish to copy part
		of the code of the Library into a program that is not
		a library.</para>

		<para>4. You may copy and distribute the Library (or a
		portion or derivative of it, under Section 2) in object
		code or executable form under the terms of Sections 1 and
		2 above provided that you accompany it with the complete
		corresponding machine-readable source code, which must be
		distributed under the terms of Sections 1 and 2 above on
		a medium customarily used for software interchange.</para>

		<para>If distribution of object code is made by offering
		access to copy from a designated place, then offering
		equivalent access to copy the source code from the same
		place satisfies the requirement to distribute the source
		code, even though third parties are not compelled to
		copy the source along with the object code.</para>

		<para>5. A program that contains no derivative of any
		portion of the Library, but is designed to work with the
		Library by being compiled or linked with it, is called a
		"work that uses the Library".  Such a work, in isolation,
		is not a derivative work of the Library, and therefore
		falls outside the scope of this License.</para>

		<para>However, linking a "work that uses the Library" with
		the Library creates an executable that is a derivative
		of the Library (because it contains portions of the
		Library), rather than a "work that uses the library".
		The executable is therefore covered by this License.
		Section 6 states terms for distribution of such
		executables.</para>

		<para>When a "work that uses the Library" uses material
		from a header file that is part of the Library, the
		object code for the work may be a derivative work
		of the Library even though the source code is not.
		Whether this is true is especially significant if the
		work can be linked without the Library, or if the work
		is itself a library.  The threshold for this to be true
		is not precisely defined by law.</para>

		<para>If such an object file uses only numerical
		parameters, data structure layouts and accessors, and
		small macros and small inline functions (ten lines or
		less in length), then the use of the object file is
		unrestricted, regardless of whether it is legally a
		derivative work.  (Executables containing this object
		code plus portions of the Library will still fall under
		Section 6.)</para>

		<para>Otherwise, if the work is a derivative of the
		Library, you may distribute the object code for the work
		under the terms of Section 6.  Any executables containing
		that work also fall under Section 6, whether or not they
		are linked directly with the Library itself.</para>

		<para>6. As an exception to the Sections above, you
		may also combine or link a "work that uses the Library"
		with the Library to produce a work containing portions
		of the Library, and distribute that work under terms of
		your choice, provided that the terms permit modification
		of the work for the customer's own use and reverse
		engineering for debugging such modifications.</para>

		<para>You must give prominent notice with each copy of the
		work that the Library is used in it and that the Library
		and its use are covered by this License.  You must supply
		a copy of this License.  If the work during execution
		displays copyright notices, you must include the copyright
		notice for the Library among them, as well as a reference
		directing the user to the copy of this License.  Also,
		you must do one of these things:</para>

		<blockquote>
			<para>a) Accompany the work with the complete
			corresponding machine-readable source code for
			the Library including whatever changes were
			used in the work (which must be distributed
			under Sections 1 and 2 above); and, if the work
			is an executable linked with the Library, with
			the complete machine-readable "work that uses
			the Library", as object code and/or source code,
			so that the user can modify the Library and then
			relink to produce a modified executable containing
			the modified Library.  (It is understood that
			the user who changes the contents of definitions
			files in the Library will not necessarily be
			able to recompile the application to use the
			modified definitions.)</para>

			<para>b) Use a suitable shared library mechanism
			for linking with the Library.  A suitable
			mechanism is one that (1) uses at run time
			a copy of the library already present on the
			user's computer system, rather than copying
			library functions into the executable, and (2)
			will operate properly with a modified version of
			the library, if the user installs one, as long as
			the modified version is interface-compatible with
			the version that the work was made with.</para>

			<para>c) Accompany the work with a written offer,
			valid for at least three years, to give the same
			user the materials specified in Subsection 6a,
			above, for a charge no more than the cost of
			performing this distribution.</para>

			<para>d) If distribution of the work is made
			by offering access to copy from a designated
			place, offer equivalent access to copy the above
			specified materials from the same place.</para>

			<para>e) Verify that the user has already
			received a copy of these materials or that you
			have already sent this user a copy.</para>
		</blockquote>

		<para>For an executable, the required form of the "work
		that uses the Library" must include any data and utility
		programs needed for reproducing the executable from it.
		However, as a special exception, the materials to be
		distributed need not include anything that is normally
		distributed (in either source or binary form) with the
		major components (compiler, kernel, and so on) of the
		operating system on which the executable runs, unless
		that component itself accompanies the executable.</para>

		<para>It may happen that this requirement contradicts
		the license restrictions of other proprietary libraries
		that do not normally accompany the operating system.
		Such a contradiction means you cannot use both them
		and the Library together in an executable that you
		distribute.</para>

		<para>7. You may place library facilities that are a work
		based on the Library side-by-side in a single library
		together with other library facilities not covered by
		this License, and distribute such a combined library,
		provided that the separate distribution of the work
		based on the Library and of the other library facilities
		is otherwise permitted, and provided that you do these
		two things:</para>

		<blockquote>
			<para>a) Accompany the combined library with
			a copy of the same work based on the Library,
			uncombined with any other library facilities.
			This must be distributed under the terms of the
			Sections above.</para>

			<para>b) Give prominent notice with the combined
			library of the fact that part of it is a work
			based on the Library, and explaining where to
			find the accompanying uncombined form of the
			same work.</para>
		</blockquote>

		<para>8. You may not copy, modify, sublicense, link with,
		or distribute the Library except as expressly provided
		under this License.  Any attempt otherwise to copy,
		modify, sublicense, link with, or distribute the Library
		is void, and will automatically terminate your rights
		under this License.  However, parties who have received
		copies, or rights, from you under this License will not
		have their licenses terminated so long as such parties
		remain in full compliance.</para>

		<para>9. You are not required to accept this License,
		since you have not signed it.  However, nothing else
		grants you permission to modify or distribute the Library
		or its derivative works.  These actions are prohibited
		by law if you do not accept this License.  Therefore,
		by modifying or distributing the Library (or any work
		based on the Library), you indicate your acceptance of
		this License to do so, and all its terms and conditions
		for copying, distributing or modifying the Library or
		works based on it.</para>

		<para>10. Each time you redistribute the Library (or any
		work based on the Library), the recipient automatically
		receives a license from the original licensor to copy,
		distribute, link with or modify the Library subject to
		these terms and conditions.  You may not impose any
		further restrictions on the recipients' exercise of
		the rights granted herein.  You are not responsible
		for enforcing compliance by third parties with this
		License.</para>

		<para>11. If, as a consequence of a court judgment or
		allegation of patent infringement or for any other reason
		(not limited to patent issues), conditions are imposed on
		you (whether by court order, agreement or otherwise) that
		contradict the conditions of this License, they do not
		excuse you from the conditions of this License.  If you
		cannot distribute so as to satisfy simultaneously your
		obligations under this License and any other pertinent
		obligations, then as a consequence you may not distribute
		the Library at all.  For example, if a patent license
		would not permit royalty-free redistribution of the
		Library by all those who receive copies directly or
		indirectly through you, then the only way you could
		satisfy both it and this License would be to refrain
		entirely from distribution of the Library.</para>

		<para>If any portion of this section is held invalid
		or unenforceable under any particular circumstance,
		the balance of the section is intended to apply, and
		the section as a whole is intended to apply in other
		circumstances.</para>

		<para>It is not the purpose of this section to induce
		you to infringe any patents or other property right
		claims or to contest validity of any such claims;
		this section has the sole purpose of protecting the
		integrity of the free software distribution system
		which is implemented by public license practices.
		Many people have made generous contributions to the
		wide range of software distributed through that system
		in reliance on consistent application of that system;
		it is up to the author/donor to decide if he or she is
		willing to distribute software through any other system
		and a licensee cannot impose that choice.</para>

		<para>This section is intended to make thoroughly clear
		what is believed to be a consequence of the rest of
		this License.</para>

		<para>12. If the distribution and/or use of the Library
		is restricted in certain countries either by patents or
		by copyrighted interfaces, the original copyright holder
		who places the Library under this License may add an
		explicit geographical distribution limitation excluding
		those countries, so that distribution is permitted only
		in or among countries not thus excluded.  In such case,
		this License incorporates the limitation as if written
		in the body of this License.</para>

		<para>13. The Free Software Foundation may publish revised
		and/or new versions of the Lesser General Public License
		from time to time.  Such new versions will be similar in
		spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail
		to address new problems or concerns.</para>

		<para>Each version is given a distinguishing version
		number.  If the Library specifies a version number
		of this License which applies to it and "any later
		version", you have the option of following the terms
		and conditions either of that version or of any later
		version published by the Free Software Foundation.
		If the Library does not specify a license version number,
		you may choose any version ever published by the Free
		Software Foundation.</para>

		<para>14. If you wish to incorporate parts of the
		Library into other free programs whose distribution
		conditions are incompatible with these, write to the
		author to ask for permission.  For software which is
		copyrighted by the Free Software Foundation, write to the
		Free Software Foundation; we sometimes make exceptions
		for this.  Our decision will be guided by the two goals
		of preserving the free status of all derivatives of our
		free software and of promoting the sharing and reuse of
		software generally.</para>

		<para>NO WARRANTY</para>

		<para>15. BECAUSE THE LIBRARY IS LICENSED FREE OF CHARGE,
		THERE IS NO WARRANTY FOR THE LIBRARY, TO THE EXTENT
		PERMITTED BY APPLICABLE LAW.  EXCEPT WHEN OTHERWISE
		STATED IN WRITING THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND/OR OTHER
		PARTIES PROVIDE THE LIBRARY "AS IS" WITHOUT WARRANTY OF
		ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, BUT NOT
		LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
		FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  THE ENTIRE RISK AS TO
		THE QUALITY AND PERFORMANCE OF THE LIBRARY IS WITH YOU.
		SHOULD THE LIBRARY PROVE DEFECTIVE, YOU ASSUME THE COST
		OF ALL NECESSARY SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION.</para>

		<para>16. IN NO EVENT UNLESS REQUIRED BY APPLICABLE
		LAW OR AGREED TO IN WRITING WILL ANY COPYRIGHT HOLDER,
		OR ANY OTHER PARTY WHO MAY MODIFY AND/OR REDISTRIBUTE
		THE LIBRARY AS PERMITTED ABOVE, BE LIABLE TO YOU FOR
		DAMAGES, INCLUDING ANY GENERAL, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL OR
		CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES ARISING OUT OF THE USE OR INABILITY
		TO USE THE LIBRARY (INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO LOSS OF
		DATA OR DATA BEING RENDERED INACCURATE OR LOSSES SUSTAINED
		BY YOU OR THIRD PARTIES OR A FAILURE OF THE LIBRARY TO
		OPERATE WITH ANY OTHER SOFTWARE), EVEN IF SUCH HOLDER
		OR OTHER PARTY HAS BEEN ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF
		SUCH DAMAGES.</para>

		<para>END OF TERMS AND CONDITIONS</para>
	</sect3>


	<sect3>
		<title>How to Apply These Terms to Your New
		Libraries</title>

		<para>If you develop a new library, and you want it to be
		of the greatest possible use to the public, we recommend
		making it free software that everyone can redistribute
		and change.  You can do so by permitting redistribution
		under these terms (or, alternatively, under the terms
		of the ordinary General Public License).</para>

		<para>To apply these terms, attach the following notices
		to the library.  It is safest to attach them to the
		start of each source file to most effectively convey
		the exclusion of warranty; and each file should have at
		least the "copyright" line and a pointer to where the
		full notice is found.</para>

		<blockquote>
			<para>&lt;one line to give the library's name
			and a brief idea of what it does.&gt;</para>

			<para>Copyright &copy; &lt;year&gt; &lt;name
			of author&gt;</para>

			<para>This library is free software; you can
			redistribute it and/or modify it under the
			terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License
			as published by the Free Software Foundation;
			either version 2.1 of the License, or (at your
			option) any later version.</para>

			<para>This library is distributed in the
			hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY
			WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
			MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR
			PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public
			License for more details.</para>

			<para>You should have received a copy of the GNU
			Lesser General Public License along with this
			library; if not, write to the Free Software
			Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330,
			Boston, MA 02111-1307 USA</para>
		</blockquote>

		<para>Also add information on how to contact you by
		electronic and paper mail.</para>

		<para>You should also get your employer (if you work
		as a programmer) or your school, if any, to sign a
		"copyright disclaimer" for the library, if necessary.
		Here is a sample; alter the names:</para>

		<blockquote>
			<para>Yoyodyne, Inc., hereby disclaims all
			copyright interest in the library `Frob' (a
			library for tweaking knobs) written by James
			Random Hacker.</para>

			<para>&lt;signature of Ty Coon&gt;, 1 April
			1990</para>

			<para>Ty Coon, President of Vice</para>
		</blockquote>

		<para>That's all there is to it!</para>
	</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</article>

